Alright, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf officially is ס"ה, Samech-He,
65, we're almost at the bottom of ס"ד עמוד א', Samech-Daled Amud
Aleph, we pick up with the two dots עד מתי הוא פוחת,
Ad masai hu pocheit, which is five lines from the bottom. We
were dealing with a very important סוגיא sugya the other day about
when the marriage is in trouble and one of the partners, focusing
on the wife, is not doing his or her responsibility and using
various means to try to either get compliance and whether we work
with that long term or we just try to move straight to
the גט, get, what we do in the interim, and so on.
And as we also mentioned the important issues, two important issues that
came up, one was: A, does the husband really have an obligation
to go find work? He has an obligation to pay the bills,
but the ואנא אפלח, V'ana Aflach, can he be forced to go
ahead and find work? And more significantly for the עגונה aguna issues,
is about when the woman basically says the marriage is intolerable. It's
one thing to say we move straight to a גט get or
she immediately loses her כתובה kesuva or so on, but how much
do we compel the husband to give a גט? get? And in
a similar discussion towards the end was compelling the husband, or תוספות
Tosafos discusses whatever,
tricking the husband or whatever, to do a חליצה chalitzah if he's
refusing to move on a situation. We now pick up at the
bottom of ס"ד עמוד א' Samech-Daled Amud Aleph with the issue about
the penalties, the financial penalties, and why they are different for the
man and the woman. So, to remind you, the משנה mishna said
that for the woman we reduce the כתובה kesuva by seven דינרין
dinarin on a weekly basis, and by the man we increase the
כתובה kesuva if he's not living up to his responsibilities. The value
increases for the benefit of the woman by three. And the other
opinion was seven and three, not דינרין, dinarin, but this thing called
טרפעיקין. tarpeikin. So the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss what טרפעיקין
tarpeikin are. But the first thing you need to know is that
a דינר dinar equals a זוז, zuz, okay?
And a זוז, zuz, I was going to bring down a whole
chart but I accidentally left it at home, but four זוז zuz
equals a
סלע, sela, okay? Or a שקל shekel בתורה. ba-Torah. Let me forget
that. Okay, a שקל shekel בתורה. ba-Torah. So when the תורה Torah
says that there's 50 שקל shekel for the bride price, for the
מוהר, mohar, it's 200 זוז. zuz. Okay,
so that's the only reason I put that up so you understand
why we get 200 זוז. zuz. But if a דינר dinar is
a זוז, zuz, so basically the כתובה kesuva is 200 זוז, zuz,
and if we reduce it by seven זוז zuz a week, that's
going to last about how long? Anybody want to do the math?
Seven divided by 200, about 25 weeks, right? No, more, 28 weeks
or something, okay, right? Seven,
two, fourteen, sixty,
right, 28 weeks.
And if we do three זוז zuz a week, then it'll last,
this is only the base amount if there's תוספת tosefes or whatever,
but anyway, if we do three זוז zuz a week, then that's
six, eighteen, twenty, about 67 weeks. Okay,
that's the first opinion about, excuse me, I did that wrong. The
three זוז zuz a week is how much we increase it for
the husband. Okay, so if we decrease it, if we're only starting
with a base כתובה kesuva of 200 and we decrease it by
seven זוז zuz a week, it'll go to zero in 28 weeks.
There might be a lot more in terms of the תוספת tosefes
and the dowry that she brings in and so on, but that's
till you get to the, that's how long it'll take to run
out the 200. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says like this: But the other opinion was not
seven זוז zuz a week but seven טרפעיקין. tarpeikin. So
מאי טרפעיקין? Mai tarpeikin? What's טרפעיקין? tarpeikin? אמר רב ששת אסטירא. Amar
Rav Sheshet: Astira. An אסטירא. astira. וכמה אסטירא? V'kama astira? How much
is an אסטירא? astira? פלגא דזוזא, Palga d'zuza, a half a זוז.
zuz. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we learned this also. רבי
יהודה אומר שלשה טרפעיקין שהן תשעה מעין. Rebbi Yehuda omer shlosha tarpeikin
shehen tisha ma'in. So it's three טרפעיקין tarpeikin
which are nine מעין, ma'in, excuse me, okay? תשעה מעין, Tisha ma'in,
מעה וחצי לכל יום. ma'ah v'chetzi l'chol yom. So it's a מעה
ma'ah and a half each day if you ignore שבת. Shabbos. Okay,
so we'll ignore the מעה ma'ah part a minute. More significant for
us is that if he says it is seven זוז, zuz, and
a זוז, zuz, excuse me, what's the matter with me today? Seven
טרפעיקין, tarpeikin, and a טרפעיקין tarpeikin is a half a זוז, zuz,
that's three and a half זוז zuz a week, right? Am I
getting this right? Okay, three and a half זוז zuz a week,
so that'll last twice as long, that'll last 56 weeks according to
him. Okay, so that's what he says. So the question is do
you reduce it by seven זוז zuz a week or by seven
half זוז zuz a week, and that's to get to the bottom
of the 200, the base amount, but as I said there's תוספת
נדוניא tosefes nedunya and whatever. Now he says that that
equals שלשה טרפעיקין, shlosha tarpeikin, excuse me,
I am so sorry people, you're not catching me, I don't know
what the heck is wrong with me. Okay, a טרפעיקין tarpeikin is,
he
says,
שלשה טרפעיקין. shlosha tarpeikin. Now why does he say שלשה טרפעיקין? shlosha
tarpeikin? In the משנה mishna he said שבעה טרפעיקין. shiva tarpeikin. Okay,
so here he's saying three for what we increase it. for the
husband. I don't know why I'm making it so difficult. Seven טרפייקין
tarpeikin is three and a half. I was right the first time.
Okay, that's for her. Okay, when he says here three טרפייקין, tarpeikin,
that's how much we increase it when he's not doing his responsibility.
So when he's not doing his responsibility, we increase it for three
זוז zuz according to the חכמים chachamim and for three טרפייקין tarpeikin
according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. That's how much we increase it,
which is nine מעין, ma'in, which is a מעה ma'ah and a
half each day. So now we're going to deal with the difference
between the three and the seven and also why we did six
days of the week and not seven days of the week. So
let's take a look. אמר ליה רבי חייא בר יוסף לשמואל: Amar
lei Rabbi Chiyya bar Yosef l'Shmuel: מאי שנא איהו, mai shna ihu,
why is it true by him, דיהבינן ליה דשבת, diyehavinan lei d'Shabbos,
that we give him, right? Because the גמרא Gemara understands logically that
if, forget now the whole טרפייקין tarpeikin versus זוז zuz which like
thing I succeeded in confusing everybody, let's forget that. The basic difference
is that whatever the coinage is, for him, if, for when she's
not doing her responsibility, it's seven that we reduce it. When he's
not doing his responsibility, we increase it by three. So there's two
implicit logics here. Number one is that if we look at the
days of the week, every day she's not doing her responsibility we
decrease it by one, either one זוז zuz or one טרפייקין, tarpeikin,
but we decrease the כתובה kesubah by one, you know, for every
day she's not doing her responsibility. For every day he is not
doing his responsibility, we increase it only by a half. Right? That,
you get that? Seven to, and we don't count שבת Shabbos for
him not doing his responsibility. So there's two questions here: why is
he being fined one when he's being fined a half? Okay, and
why is she being fined for שבת Shabbos when he's not being
fined for שבת? Shabbos? That's the key question. Forget the טרפייק tarpeik
thing, that was just confusing. Whether it's זוז zuz or טרפייקין, tarpeikin,
the difference is one versus a half and whether you do it
for שבת Shabbos or not. So מאי שנא, mai shna, where were
we?
איהו דיהבינן ליה דשבת, ihu diyehavinan lei d'Shabbos, why when she's not
doing her responsibility does he get for שבת, Shabbos, meaning she gets
fined for שבת Shabbos which benefits him? ומאי שנא איהי דלא יהבינן
לה דשבת, U'mai shna ihi d'lo yehavinan lah d'Shabbos, when it's she
that is the injured party, she doesn't get for שבת? Shabbos? So
גמרא Gemara says, איהו דמפחת קא פחית לא מחזי כשכר שבת, ihu
d'mifchas ka pachis lo michzi k'schar Shabbos, because when
she, when he's, when she's doing the wrong thing and we're reducing
the כתובה, kesubah, to reduce a debt doesn't look like you're getting
paid for something on שבת. Shabbos. If there, debt he's benefiting from
it from the fact that the day שבת Shabbos is being deducted,
that extra, that extra זוז, zuz, but it doesn't look like he's
being paid for anything on שבת. Shabbos. It's just that the debt
is being reduced. איהי דאוסופי קא מוסי, ihi d'osufi ka mosi, when
he is not doing his responsibility and we're fining him, so if
we were to fine him for שבת, Shabbos, מחזי כשכר שבת, michzi
k'schar Shabbos, then the fact that on שבת Shabbos she is essence
earning a half of a, you know, he's earning a half of
a זוז zuz off of him, right? If he was being paying
a half a זוז zuz a day including שבת, Shabbos, if we
were increasing the debt when he's not doing his responsibility, then she's
effectively earning money on שבת. Shabbos. That's, that's the concern. Do you,
just, do you get that? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
now what's the difference between a whole and a half? אמר ליה
רבי חייא בר יוסף לשמואל מה בין מורד למורדת? Amar lei Rabbi
Chiyya bar Yosef l'Shmuel: mah bein mored l'moredes? Why is there a
difference between a מורד mored and a מורדת? moredes? That for, for
her, she gets fined one זוז zuz a day including שבת Shabbos
as we've said. For him, he gets fined only a half זוז
zuz a day and not including שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר ליה צא ולמד משוק של זונות, amar lei: tzei u'lamad
mishuk shel zonos, go see from the marketplace of the prostitutes, מי
שוכר את מי, mi socher es mi, who hires out who? The
men, right, there's a much bigger market for female prostitutes than for
male prostitutes. Okay, so the men are hiring the women and therefore
what does that prove? So רש״י Rashi says, therefore assuming that we're
dealing that מורד mored and מורדת moredes is about withholding sex, he's
seen to be the much more injured party. That men are seen
here as ones having much greater sexual desire and therefore they're the
ones that are being much more injured if in a case where
one of the parties is withholding sex. דבר אחר זה יצרו מבחוץ
וזה יצרה מבפנים. Davar acher: zeh yitzro mibachutz v'zeh yitzrah mibifnim.
The other issue is that this one's genitals is on the outside
and the other's on the inside. What does that mean? Either you
could say it's symbolic of the fact of who has a greater
sex drive in the eyes of the גמרא Gemara or, as רש״י
Rashi says, קשוייו ניכר ומתגנה, kishuyo nikar u'misganeh,
if the husband might, you know, he will, if he's having an
erection and he's not getting sexual satisfaction, it's more obvious to people
than if the woman is not. So somehow he is seen here
as the more injured party. Interestingly, although he has a מצוה mitzvah
of עונה, onah, he is seen as the more injured party when
sex is being withheld and therefore he is, she is fined double
when she is the one that's withholding sex than what he is
fined. Okay, so two differences: she's, he's, she's fined double, one per
day, him only a half per day, and she's fined on שבת
Shabbos because it doesn't look like anybody's earning money because a debt
is being reduced, whereas he's not fined on שבת Shabbos because that
then does look like she's earning money on שבת, Shabbos, as it
were. Yes?
They're concerned about שבת Shabbos wages, but they're not concerned about יום
טוב? Yom Tov?
That's a good question. I don't know what to say. תוספות Tosfos
anyway raises the issue that why don't we just have הבדלה? Havdalah?
It's not ניכר. nikar. We're not treating שבת Shabbos separately. Anyway, whatever
it is, bottom line, again you have once again this sort of,
you know, disparity, imbalance between the man and the woman in the
amount that it's being fined, also, you know, to add to the
fact of course that the man can always do the divorce, you
know, initiate a divorce which the woman cannot as we discussed yesterday.
And the question is about how quickly is the כתובה Kesuva being
reduced from the 200 based on whether it's seven זוז zuz or
seven טרפעיק terpayaik which are seven half זוז. zuz. We're talking about
between a half year to a year if you were to go
through the process in the משנה, Mishna, let alone if there was
a תוספת tosefes and a נדוניא nedunya and so on. In the
גמרא Gemara of course we saw versions that it was a much
faster process, we didn't want to schlep it out, we wanted to
move much more quickly to the גט. get. Yes.
What about all these currencies? They're all different from different times and
different places?
Some of them are, yeah. I had meant actually printed out, there's
a very nice, if you go on the web, on I think
Hebrew Wikipedia they have a very nice discussion of all the different
currencies and whatever. I printed out a chart but then of course
I left it at home. Yes.
Does the value of the coins change in part because of international
inflation and part because of deliberate attempts to debase the coinage?
Aha. Okay, moving on.
What is הבלעה? havla'ah? What does that mean?
That's when you pay for services done on שבת Shabbos but you
don't single out שבת, Shabbos, it's part of a payment for the
rest of the week as well. Okay, let's move on. We're going
to catch up today. Next משנה. Mishna. Okay, so we sort of
are jumping back and forth. It's like a chiastic structure because first
if you remember we did a משנה Mishna that said what are
the woman's domestic responsibilities? Then we said we spoke about his obligation
of עונה. onah. Then we spoke about מורד mored and מורדת moredes
where the גמרא Gemara in the last line clearly made the assumption
although it was debated that we're talking primarily about the issue about
not having sex. So we did מלאכה, melacha, sex, sex, right? Obligations
of עונה, onah, not having עונה. onah. And now we're dealing with
ways back to the issue about מלאכה melacha and מזונות. mezonos. So
let's take a look. And this is the counterpart of מזונות, mezonos,
his obligations to provide for her. So המשרה אשתו על ידי שליח.
Hamashreh ishto al yedei shaliach. Somebody is basically providing for his wife
through a intermediary. They are not sharing actual domicile. If they're sharing
domicile then mostly this is a moot point. They just have their
meals together. But for whatever reason, maybe he's away on a business
trip, maybe they're working things out, who knows what the reasons are,
she is not living in his house, okay, and he is having
somebody basically pay her food bills and provide for her. So what
therefore is his minimum obligations to her? לא יפחות לה משני קבין
חטים. Lo yifchos la mi-shnei kabin chitin. He cannot pay any less
than give her less than two קב kav which is some type
of a volume measurement of wheat or מארבעה קבין שעורים me-arba'ah kabin
se'orin or four קב kav of barley if she prefers, presumably if
he gets to choose if she prefers barley to wheat. Barley was
seen as obviously as not as ideal of a grain. אמר רבי
יוסי לא פסק לה שעורים אלא רבי ישמעאל שהיה סמוך לאדום. Amar
Rabbi Yosi lo pasak la se'orin ela Rabbi Yishmael she-hayah samuch le-Edom.
Okay, the only one who said that she gets barley is
Rabbi Yishmael who was close to Edom. What'd that have to do
with anything? We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. ונותן לה חצי קב
קטנית Ve-nosein la chatzi kav kitnis and he gives her a half
of a קב kav of קטנית kitnis of legumes. We all know
what קטנית kitnis are. וחצי לוג שמן Ve-chatzi log shemen and a
half לוג log of oil. This is per week. A לוג log
is when we, you know, say on שבת Shabbos you need to
have a רביעית, revi'is, that's a רביעית revi'is of a לוג. log.
So a רביעית revi'is is about three and a half ounces. So
a half of a לוג log is about whatever, seven ounces. Seven
ounces of oil.
וקב גרוגרות Ve-kav grogeros
and a קב kav of גרוגרות grogeros which are dried figs or
מנה דבלה maneh deveilah or if she prefers or maybe I don't
prefer, it's in season, whatever, if she prefers dates to figs then
a מנה maneh which is a weight measurement of pressed dates. ואם
אין לו Ve-im ein lo and let's say he doesn't have actually
those fruits directly
available, פוסק לעומתן פירות ממקום אחר, posek le-umasan peiros mi-makom acher, then
he gives her the equivalent amount from other types of fruit. ונותן
לה מטה מפץ ומחצלת. Ve-nosein la mitah mapatz u-machatzeles. So that's in
terms of her food, the minimum amount he has to provide for
her food-wise. ונותן לה מטה מפץ ומחצלת, Ve-nosein la mitah mapatz u-machatzeles,
he gives her a bed, a mat, and a, like a, you
know, these are different types of a mat, some type of a
cushion and a mat. ונותן לה כיפה לראשה, Ve-nosein la kippah le-roshah,
gives her some type of a covering for her head וחגור למתניה
ve-chagor le-mosneha and a belt for her loins ומנעלים. u-man'alayim. So again,
not questioning exactly how frequently. The implicit part was the first part
was on a weekly basis although notice it never actually did say
weekly. Presumably you don't have to give her a new מטה מפץ
ומחצלת mitah mapatz u-machatzeles on a weekly basis. So presumably that's if
she doesn't have. So and now that we're talking about the more,
what are these called, durables rather than consumables, is that the phrase?
Now that we're more sort of in the durable category again, it's
not clear exactly the frequency, but now when we get to the
shoes and the clothing, we return—the frequency is more explicit. And shoes,
ממועד למועד, mi-mo'ed le-mo'ed, new shoes every רגל. regel. וכלים של חמישים
זוז, ve-kelim shel chamishim zuz, משנה לשנה, mi-shanah le-shanah, and clothes, new
clothes of fifty זוז zuz every year. ואין נותנין לה לא חדשים
בימות החמה ולא שחקים בימות הגשמים. ve-ein notnin lah lo chadashim bi-ymot
ha-chamah ve-lo shechakim bi-ymot ha-geshamim. Don't give her new clothes in the
summer because new clothes were thicker, they hadn't been worn thin yet,
so therefore they were warmer. So don't give her those clothes in
the summer, and don't give her the worn clothes which are thinner
in the winter, but that's when they're on sale. אלא נותנין לה
כלים של חמישים זוז בימות
הגשמים, ela notnin lah kelim shel chamishim zuz bi-ymot ha-geshamim, buy the
new clothes of fifty זוז zuz in the
winter, והיא מתכסה בבלותיהן בימות החמה, ve-hi mitkasah be-valoteihen bi-ymot ha-chamah, and
then she can use them as they're worn out towards the end
of the—in the summer when you want worn out clothes. והשחקים שלה,
ve-ha-shechakim she-lah, and then at when you buy presumably the end of
the year and you buy new clothes, she gets to keep the
old worn out ones that had been used from last year. נותן
לה מעה כסף לצרכה, noten lah ma'ah kesef le-tzarkhah, plus, we had
mentioned this before, she gets an extra מעה ma'ah of money for
every, you know, every week, like pin money for whatever small needs
she might have. And that's on a weekly basis, we're back to
the implicit weekly basis. ואוכלת עמו מלילי שבת ללילי שבת, ve-ochelet immo
mi-leilei shabbat le-leilei shabbat, and even if he is for whatever reason
they're living apart, he has to make a point of eating at
least one meal together on every Friday night, which is quite interesting,
right? Because you would sort of say, well, that makes a lot
of sense, like the—you know, we want to sort of have them
to have some type of a continued personal relationship. But it is
interesting that we can sort of like dictate it. I mean, I
guess why not? We can dictate that they have to have sex
at regular intervals, we might as well dictate that they have to
eat together at regular intervals. But again, that is interesting. It's something
that we're not used—you know, is—it falls under like the rubric of
like פרנסה parnasah is not just paying the bills maybe, but a
certain amount of actually spending some time together, you know, at the
table. Okay,
so—right, isn't that what people are trying to do, encourage everybody to
have at least one meal a week? Like, you know, learn from
the Jews, one type of a meal of the week, no TV,
no whatever, everybody's just together at the table.
Exactly, we sort of figured that one out. Okay, so that's the
Friday night meal. והשחקים שלה
מה הם?
ve-ha-shechakim she-lah mah
hem? Meaning, at the end of the year you buy new clothes
and she gets to keep the worn out ones.
He doesn't say—והשחקים שלה. ve-ha-shechakim she-lah. Right.
Okay. ואם אין נותן לה מעה כסף לצרכה,
ve-im ein noten lah ma'ah
kesef le-tzarkhah, and if he doesn't give her the מעה כסף ma'ah
kesef for the pin money here, מעשי ידיה שלה, ma'aseh yadeha she-lah,
she keeps the מעשה ידיים. ma'aseh yadayim. If you remember before, there
was a whole question whether that literally means she keeps the מעשה
ידיים ma'aseh yadayim or whether it means she keeps the מותר מעשה
ידיים, motar ma'aseh yadayim, what she earns over her basic obligations. ומה
היא עושה לו? u-mah hi osah lo? What is the work that
she does in the house? Now again, it's funny because we already
listed all the work—she bakes, she sews, she knits, you know, whatever.
I mean, it was this whole—she does the laundry, a huge list.
So this here is the מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim as I've mentioned
before, which seems to also be a fixed amount, but also be
probably something that she could earn, bring in some money, you know,
into the house, into the house. She could actually, you know,
earn
money from outside the house with.
So—so what does she do? So ומה היא עושה לו? u-mah hi
osah lo? משקל חמש סלעים שתי ביהודה שהן עשר סלעים בגליל. mishkal
chamesh sla'im sheti bi-yehudah she-hen eser sla'im ba-galil.
So here is again different weights. In גליל, galil, the weights were
half as much as in יהודה. yehudah. So something that weighs five
סלעים—dealing sla'im with the—the שתי, sheti, I forget if it's warp or
woof. Anyway, one of them. Anyway, five סלע sela worth of that
weight in יהודה, yehudah, which is ten סלע sela worth in גליל,
galil, because in גליל galil the weights were half as much. Okay,
so she has to produce that much of like weaving. או משקל
עשר סלעים ערב ביהודה שהן עשרים סלעים בגליל. o mishkal eser sla'im
erev bi-yehudah she-hen esrim sla'im ba-galil.
Or ten not of the שתי sheti but of the ערב erev
or the other way around. Which way is it? Which one—Charlie, what
does the משנה mishnah say? What do you got there in your
English?
I keep on getting confused which is which. The
woof is
easier to prepare.
Okay, so it's—so it's—so it's five of the warp or ten of
the woof. Okay fine. Wait, what? The woof—if it's easier to prepare,
it's the bigger one.
It's the more—doesn't matter.
Nobody knows what it means anyway. Okay, moving on. Okay. שהן עשרים
סלעים בגליל. she-hen esrim sla'im ba-galil.
The warp is fixed in the loom.
Okay, so five.
So the woof would go back—it's thinner,
it goes
back—all right fine. ואם הייתה מניקה פוחתין לה ממעשה ידיה ומוסיפין לה
על מזונותיה. ve-im hayetah meinikah pochtin lah mi-ma'aseh yadeha u-mosifin lah al
mezonoteha. So fine. That's anyway—that's the amount of sewing or whatever weaving
that she has to do. And again, that's the amount that—that's like
I said, that seems to be the one that's singled out here
in terms of—in
terms—because that's the thing that—that, you know, she could actually earn money
from. It's not just the inside the house domestic duty. So if
you ask me, by the way, the פשט pshat So if you
ask me, by the way, the פשט pshat of the משנה mishna
is not like either the two opinions in the גמרא. gemara. If
you remember before, there were two opinions in the גמרא: gemara: is
the סלע כסף sela kesef כנגד k'neged the מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim
or כנגד k'neged the מותר מעשה ידיים? mosar ma'aseh yadayim? Right, it's
only a little bit of money, so you would think that it's
probably כנגד k'neged the מותר מעשה ידיים, mosar ma'aseh yadayim, not the
עיקר מעשה ידיים ikkar ma'aseh yadayim and so on. I would say
that the פשט pshat in the משנה mishna is it's כנגד k'neged
the מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim but only the מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim
of the weaving and of the money that she's bringing in, not
of the מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim of the basic domestic duties. But
that was never really fully spelled out in the גמרא, gemara, the
difference between labeling the basic domestic responsibilities as מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim
or labeling the earning that she's making by bringing money in from
outside the house as the מעשה ידיים, ma'aseh yadayim, which is what
is being done here.
Okay. Now, ואם הייתה מניקה, v'im hayta menika, if she was nursing,
פוסקין לה ממעשה ידיה, poskin lah mima'aseh yadeha, she has to do
less work because, a, just because she's doing more work in one
area that's less work in another, but also more importantly, because if
she's doing all this work, it might not, it might impact her
ability to nurse well. So it's not just like it's got to
be fair and I'm doing more here, I do less somewhere else,
but actually because it because it compromises her ability to nurse. ומוסיפין
לה על מזונותיה, u'mosifin lah al mezonoteha, and you actually give her
an increase in her food allowance because she has to eat for
two. במה דברים אמורים, b'meh devarim amurim, when is this true? בעני
שבישראל, be'ani she'be'yisrael, all of these minimums are somebody who is poor
and has, so we're talking about the minimum. אבל במכובד, aval bi'mechubad,
if somebody is of a higher status, then הכל לפי כבודו, hakol
l'fi kvodo, it all goes according to his status or her status,
as we've seen. Okay. מני מתניתין? mani matnitin? Who is our משנה?
mishna? לא רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא ולא רבי שמעון, lo Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka v'lo Rabbi Shimon, not Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, not Rabbi
Shimon that gives this as a קב kav of חטין chittin for
her food.
דתנן, d'tenan, we talk in the משנה: mishna: וכמה שיעורו, v'kamah shi'uro,
how much is the שיעור shi'ur for the עירוב תחומין? eruv techumin?
Which has to be the שיעור shi'ur of שתי סעודות. shtei se'udot.
So what makes two meals' worth? מזון שתי סעודות לכל אחד ואחד.
mazon shtei se'udot l'chol echad v'echad.
So everybody who is using the עירוב תחומין eruv techumin has to
contribute שתי סעודות shtei se'udot per person who wants to make an
עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. מזונו לחול ולא לשבת, m'zono l'chol v'lo l'shabbat,
דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, and it's the amount of food
you would eat on the weekday, not on שבת, Shabbat, that's what
Rabbi Meir says. This is specifically about bread, we'll see. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, לשבת ולא לחול, l'shabbat v'lo l'chol, no, it's
the amount of bread you would eat on שבת, Shabbat, not on
a weekday at a meal. That's how you measure the two meals.
וזה וזה מתכוונים להקל, v'zeh v'zeh mitkavnim l'hakkel, and each one is
trying to be lenient. What does that mean? That one says you
eat more on שבת, Shabbat, so therefore you have the bread that
you eat during the weekday, that's a smaller amount. And the other
says, yeah, but on שבת Shabbat you eat more, you eat more
of different types of dishes, so you actually eat less bread. So
the amount of bread that you actually eat is less on שבת
Shabbat than it is during the weekday. Okay.
So now the גמרא gemara says, okay, but whatever it is, it's
two meals. Now, how much does two meals of bread translate into?
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka omer, כיכר הלקוח
בפונדיון, kikar ha'lakuach b'pundiyon, the amount that you determine of what is
two meals is the loaf of bread that is purchased with
a
פונדיון, pundiyon, when four סאה se'ah of grain goes to a סלע,
sela, it costs a סלע. sela. So basically, let me save you
the math here, try to do it a little better than last
time. A סלע sela is 48 פונדיון. pundiyon. ארבע סאים, arba sa'im,
a סאה se'ah is six קב. kav. So basically he is saying
when you have 24 קב kav of wheat
going for 48
פונדיון, pundiyon, okay, then therefore, okay, which basically means, what does it
mean? It means that one קב kav is two פונדיון, pundiyon, okay,
yes? So therefore he says how much therefore, and how much
is
a bread worth two meals? So he says כיכר הלקוח בפונדיון. kikar
ha'lakuach b'pundiyon. So if you can buy a כיכר kikar with a
פונדיון, pundiyon, it is one loaf
made
out of a half of a קב kav of wheat is two
meals. Okay, so a half of a קב kav of wheat is
two meals.
Take out the one here. A loaf of a half of a
קב kav of wheat is two meals. That's what he says. Okay,
that's for him two meals, a bread made out of a half
of a קב kav of wheat. Yeah, it would have been. Okay.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, שתי ידות
בכיכר, shtei yadot b'kikar, two-thirds of a loaf of bread, משלוש כיכרות
לקב, mishalosh kikarot l'kav, when three loaves make up a קב. kav.
So for him, so the first one was who?
Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka. Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka. Who's the next one?
Rabbi Shimon. Rabbi Shimon. He says two-thirds of a
loaf when what does he say? When it's three. Three loaves per
קב. kav. So if it's three loaves per קב, kav, it's a
half of a it's a third of a קב kav per loaf.
So that means for him, right, that is, so for two meals...
okay, all of this is two meals. I'll put the two meals
here. Okay, for him it is a half of a... here, the
first one is a half of a קב kav and this is
two-ninths of a קב. kav. Big difference.
Right, everybody see that? If it's one loaf at a half of
a קב, kav, it's a half of a קב. kav. If it's
two-thirds of a loaf at a third of a קב kav per
loaf, that's two-ninths of a קב. kav. Those are their different opinions
about what makes two meals. Pretty big difference. Okay, less than half
this opinion is. It's a small loaf. Okay, right. So, חצייה לבית
המנוגע, chatziyah le-veit ha-menuga,
half of this is for how long it you have to wait,
the amount of time it takes to eat half of a loaf
is the amount of time it takes to eat a meal. Now
half of a loaf is a, what's the word for half in
Aramaic? פרס. pras. So, when we say, everyone heard the phrase כדי
אכילת פרס, kedei achilat pras, that means eating half of a loaf
of bread, assuming the loaf of bread is two meals. Half of
a loaf is one meal. So כדי אכילת פרס kedei achilat pras
is the amount of time it takes you to eat a half
a loaf of bread, meaning a meal's worth of bread. Okay, so
whatever your two your loaf is, it's a loaf that's satisfying you
for two meals. Half of that is going to be the amount
that you have to wait in the house of a that has
צרעת tzaraat to become טמא, tamei, because if you wait there the
time it takes you to eat a meal, you become טמא. tamei.
But actually, as we know, as I've said, כדי אכילת פרס kedei
achilat pras is a much broader definition in many other areas. So,
חצייה לבית המנוגע, chatziyah le-veit ha-menuga, וחצי חצייה, ve-chatzi chatziyah, half of
the half, לפסול את הגוייה. lifsol et ha-guviyah. So if you eat
a quarter of that loaf, half of a meal, of טמא tamei
food, you become טמא. tamei. Okay, I don't want to get into
that. וחצי חצי חצייה, ve-chatzi chatzi chatziyah, and half of the half
of the half. So okay, that is an eighth of that loaf,
or it's a it's a quarter of a meal, לקבל טומאת אוכלין,
lekabbel tum'at ochlin, that is the amount of food that can become
טמא tamei as foodstuff, which according to Rashi is a ביצה. beitzah.
Okay, anyway, we'll skip that part. מני, manei, we won't focus on
it. אי רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא תמני הוויין. ei Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka tamni havyan. אי רבי שמעון תמני סרי הוויין. ei Rabbi Shimon
tamni srei havyan. So we said how many קב kav did we
say in the Mishnah of wheat? We said two קבין, kavvin, right?
משני קבין חיטין mishnei kavvin chitin or or four קב kav of
barley. But two קבין kavvin of wheat. So let's figure out: according
to him, a half according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka, a half a קב kav is two meals. So two
קבין kavvin is how many meals? Two קבין kavvin is to you
how much is if a half of קב kav is two, two
קבין kavvin is four times that is eight meals. Okay, according to
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, two-ninths of a קב kav is two meals.
So therefore, let's figure how you figure this out. Two-ninths of a
קב, kav,
every one-ninth of a קב kav is one meal. Okay, there's got
to be an easier way to do this. It's eighteen. Yeah, but
how there's an easier way how do you do this?
You divide two by two...
okay, two קבים kavvin is nine meals. No, two-ninths of a קב
kav is two meals, which means
one-ninth of a
קב kav is one meal, which means one קב kav is nine
meals.
Okay, so two קבים kavvin is eighteen meals. Okay, so either according
to him, you know, two קבים kavvin is going to be eight,
and according to him two קבים kavvin is going to be eighteen.
Okay, big difference. But also, neither is the Mishnah because because if
you need bread for a week, there's only fourteen meals in a
week, or fifteen if you have סעודה שלישית seudah shlishit on Shabbos.
So that's the Gemara's problem. It assumes fourteen meals a week and
it says you either have too few too little bread according to
him or too much bread according to him. So how does it
work? Let's take a look.
Okay, אי רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא תמני הוויין. ei Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka tamni havyan. אי רבי שמעון תמני סרי הוויין, ei Rabbi Shimon
tamni srei havyan, it's eighteen. לעולם רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא. le-olam Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. Really it's רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka that we said came to eight.
וכדאמר רב חסדא צא מהן
שליש לחנווני. u-kede'amar Rav Chisda tzei me-hen shelish la-chanvani. Take out a
third for the storekeeper. Okay, so what does that mean? It means
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka did not say that
there's actually a half a קב kav of wheat in the loaf
of bread. What he actually said was the loaf of bread cost
a פונדיון pundion and wheat is going at twenty-four קב kav to
a סלע, sela, which means what about the profit of the baker?
What about the profit of the storekeeper? He's not telling you how
much wheat went in; he's telling you the price of wheat. So
the Gemara says if you factor in the profit of the baker,
then actually when you're paying one פונדיון pundion for a loaf of
bread, you're actually getting less than a קב, kav, right, because he's
not using the the entire money you gave him to buy the
wheat ingredient; what about his effort? So he's only using two-thirds of
the money you gave him to actually buy the wheat, the rest
he's pocketing. So let's read this. So it
says a third of the money you give him is going... towards
his profit. So he's not going to buy the wheat. So הכא
נמי hacha nami take a third, שדי עילויה, shadei iluvei, add it
to it, אכתי akati תריסר הוי. trisar havei. It's 12, meaning so
for him it's that amount of wheat that you... that amount
two קב kav of... let me see if I can explain this
in a way that's not confusing. I know it's very confusing. Two
קב, kav, you give her two קב, kav, it doesn't make eight
meals. You give her two קב, kav, it makes 12 meals. If
you were to buy that from the storekeeper, right? He'd sell you
eight because he's profiting a third, a quarter, a third of it
for his own profit. Okay, so when he says... okay, we'll just
work with that. Okay.
Maybe the פונדיון pundion is the wholesale price?
No, no, no. The פונדיון pundion is what you pay the retailer,
but the point is he is telling you what the bread
costs at the retailer price. Exactly, how much flour is converted at
the
wholesale price?
Exactly, exactly. So when he says that this is the rate, this
is only the rate at the retail price. Like, that's maybe the
easy way to think about this. This is the retail rate, this
is what... and not only retail, this is already went into
loaf, but the actual amount of flour that you get is actually
a third more and therefore the amount of meals is... whatever, I'm
confused already. Anyway, fine. Okay, the point is that once you factor
in the profit, really he's saying that that amount of wheat will
produce 12 loaves of bread, not 8 loaves of bread, 12 meals,
not 8 meals.
But he even went so far as to say how much flour...
I understand, which is what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said. And רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka gets you confusing because he's
talking about the market price. Anyway, so בקיצור, bekitzur, according to him,
it's not really eight. That amount of flour actually gets you 12
meals, not 8 meals. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but
12 is 12, it's not 14. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
אוכלת עמו לליל שבת. ochelet imo laleil Shabbat. No,
but you eat on שבת. Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
but that's only Friday night, that only gets you 13. So the
גמרא Gemara says, הניחא למאן דאמר אכילה ממש, haniucha leman deamar achila
mamash, that's anyway if אכילה achila literally means that they eat together.
אלא למאן דאמר אכילה תשמיש, ela leman deamar achila tashmish, and some
say אכילה achila is a euphemism in the משנה. Mishna. It means
that they get together and have sex on Friday night. So מאי
איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? You still only have 12 meals. ועוד,
veod, even if you are eating together Friday night, תליסר הוי, tlisar
havei, it's only 13 meals. אלא כי הא דאמר רב חסדא, ela
ki ha deamar Rav Chisda, fine. צא מהם מחצה לחנווני. tzei mehem
mechtza lachinvani. So it's not the first version of רב חסדא Rav
Chisda that the storekeeper is profiting a third, actually the storekeeper is
getting... is profiting a half, that only half of the money goes
towards the wheat, the other half he pockets.
Okay. What? אונאה? ona'ah? No, אונאה ona'ah is when you charge more
than the going rate. The גמרא Gemara will describe later why it
might be a half and it might be a third. But the
גמרא Gemara says, I don't know, when you go to a restaurant,
how much do you think they actually pay for the raw ingredients?
Probably about 10... about 2% of actually what the bill is. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי hacha nami take half, ושדי
עילויה. vashadei iluvei. So and you add to it, so now instead
of 8 you're going to get 16. Of course 16 is too
much. So we'll take a look. גמרא Gemara says, first of all
קשיא דרב חסדא ארב חסדא. kashya deRav Chisda aRav Chisda. First of
all, what? Is he contradicting himself? Are we assuming the storekeeper is
getting a half profit or a third profit? So the גמרא Gemara
says, לא קשיא הא באתרא דאייתי ציבי הא באתרא דלא אייתי ציבי.
lo kashya ha beatra deayiti tzivei ha beatra dela ayiti tzivei. It
depends whether the storekeeper, when he buys the flour, does the provider
of the flour throw in the firewood for free or not? If
the guy throws in the firewood, he makes a bigger profit. If
the guy doesn't throw in the firewood, then he has to spend
more expenses on the firewood. All right, anyway, בקיצור, bekitzur, back to
our point, אי הכי שיתסר הוי. ei hachi shitsar havei. So what
we've basically said is רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka,
it sounded like you're only going to get 8 meals out of
that amount of wheat, but then we realized no, no, no, that's
what you get when you buy it as a produced bread because
the guy's profiting, but really that amount of wheat produces not 8
meals but it really produces double, 16 meals. Okay? So the woman
is getting 16 meals of bread, but she only needs 14 meals
of bread. So we still don't understand it. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אי הכי שיתסר הוי, ei hachi shitsar havei, it's 16 meals
and we only need 14. כמאן כרבי חדקא? keman keRabbi Chidka? It's
going like רבי חדקא? Rabbi Chidka? דאמר ארבע סעודות חייב אדם לאכול
בשבת. deamar arba seudot chayav adam leechol beShabbat. You don't have to
have three meals on שבת, Shabbat, you have to have four meals
on שבת. Shabbat. Okay? So you go from your normal 14 to
16. And then the גמרא Gemara says, אפילו תימא רבנן, afilu teima
rabbanan, you know, even if it's the rabbis that say only three
meals on שבת, Shabbat, so why is it 16 and not 15?
חדא לאורחי ופרחי, chada leorchi ufarchei, you have one extra amount measure
of bread in case a guest drops by, so that's why it's
16 meals worth of bread. השתא דאתית להכי, hashta deatit lehachi, now
that we're mentioning this, אפילו תימא רבי שמעון, afilu teima Rabbi Shimon,
even according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, remember רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
said you would get 18 meals out of... for רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon out of that amount of bread? So now we understand how
why 18. לרבנן leRabbanan for the rabbis who say three סעודות seudot
on שבת, Shabbat, so you start with the idea of 15 meals
during the week, דל תלת לאורחי ופרחי, dal telat leorchi ufarchei, so
you get three extra loaves of bread for guests who might drop
by. רבי חדקא, Rabbi Chidka, and רבי חדקא Rabbi Chidka says that
there are four meals on שבת, Shabbat, so you have 14 meals,
so
דל תרתי. dal tarti. he is responsible for providing her not only
for her own food but
for
a
possible guest, yeah that is interesting. Not her children. Not her children.
We're going to get to children, but that's a very good point.
Yeah, that is interesting that there is a little extra thrown in
for the guest. Okay, anyway, one way or another we figured out
that it's the amount of bread that she needs to manage for
a week, 14, you know, 14 meals plus שבת Shabbos 15, maybe
you get up to 16 or 18, but the amount of bread
that goes with every single meal of the week. What I should
mention, you know, what's absent from this משנה? mishna? What's absent from
this משנה? mishna? She basically for every meal gets a loaf of
bread, either of wheat or of barley, right? And then she gets
what else does she get? Some legumes, some oil, some dates or
figs. Okay, that's basically what she gets. What isn't she getting? Wine.
Well, forget wine, she isn't getting any protein, she doesn't get any
fish or meat or whatever.
What? For the vegans in us, you'd be very happy with it,
okay? No eggs, no milk, I'm serious, no cheese, I'm serious, totally,
it's a very barebones. I mean, this says עני שבישראל, ani sheb'Yisrael,
but this is very, very barebones, right? It's
basically starch and a little bit of fruit. Where were the vegetables
also? How about vegetables, huh? Rabbi Dolph, can you relate to that
problem? There are no vegetables. Okay.
So what's the אורחי ופרחי archi uparchi when they fly in?
No, yeah, it means passersby. Okay, moving on. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar
Rebbi Yose, so now we had either that amount of wheat or
twice that amount, or twice that amount of barley. And רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yose says, no, no, no, the barley was only for רבי
ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael who lived near אדום. Edom. So what does that
mean? So גמרא Gemara says, אלא דאדום הוא דאכלין שעורין בכל העולם
לא אכלי? ela d'Edom hu d'achlin seorin b'chol ha'olam lo achli? What
do you mean? Only in אדום Edom they eat barley, nowhere else?
הכי קאמר לא פסק שעורין כפליים בחיטים. hachi ka'amar lo pasak seorin
kiflayim b'chitim. The reason the משנה mishna said that if you give
barley it's double the amount of wheat, אלא רבי ישמעאל שהיה סמוך
לאדום, ela Rebbi Yishmael shehaya samuch l'Edom, that only רבי ישמעאל Rebbi
Yishmael said that, מפני ששעוריהן אדומיות רעות הן, mipnei she'seoreihen Adomiyot ra'ot
hen, because their barley was very poor quality, so if you wanted
to have the equivalent barley to wheat it has to be double
measure, but elsewhere it would not have to be double measure, be
some other measure. Okay, so that's the basic bread that you're providing
her for a daily basis, or a weekly basis. ונותן לה חצי
קב קטנית, v'noten lah chatzi kav kitnit, a half of a קב
kav of legumes. ואילו יין לא קתני. v'ilu yayin lo katanei. See,
it's not bothered by me about the vegetables or about the protein,
it's worried about the wine.
מסייע ליה לרבי אלעזר, Mesayei lei l'Rebbi Elazar, this supports רבי אלעזר.
Rebbi Elazar. דאמר רבי אלעזר, D'amar Rebbi Elazar, אין פוסקין יינות לאשה,
ein poskin yeinot l'ishah, you do not, when a woman is living
separate from her husband and he is paying for the food, you
do not give her out wine. פוסקין poskin also is like a
directive to בית דין. beis din. The husband maybe is away and
hasn't made arrangements for his wife, and the בית דין beis din
has to determine what are we going to do, take from his
property, you know, in order to provide for her. So what we
do not provide for her is wine.
ואם תאמר, V'im tomar, and
if
you
say
אלכה אחרי מאהבי נותני לחמי ומימי צמרי ופשתי שמני ושקויי,
elcha acharei me'ahavai notnei lachmi umaymai
tzamri ufishti shamni v'shikuyai, let me go to those who love me,
who give me my bread and my water,
my wool and linen,
my oil and my drink. So you see there that it indicates
that women would drink wine, and not necessarily that פסוק pasuk is
referring to a very, you know, a very virtuous woman. But be
that as it may, דברים שהאשה משתוקקת עליהן, devarim she'ha'ishah mishtokeket aleihen,
that doesn't mean wine, שקויי shikuyai means things that a woman desires.
ומאי ניהו תכשיטין, U'mai nihu tachshitin, that means jewelry, but you do
not give her wine. דרש רבי יהודה איש כפר נביריא, Darash Rebbi
Yehuda ish Kfar Nevirya, ואמרי לה איש כפר נפור חייא, v'amrei lah
ish Kfar Nafor Chaya, מנין שאין פוסקין יינות
לאשה? minayin she'ein poskin yeinot l'ishah? How do you know that you
do not, sort of, give wine, you know, the בית דין beis
din does not allocate wine to a woman? Again, and this is
regardless of the status or the wealth of the husband, but that
we've decided that's a dangerous thing because we're going to see in
a minute we assume that it will lead to licentious behavior. שנאמר
ותקם חנה אחרי אכלו בשילה ואחרי
שתו, shene'emar vatakam Chanah acharei ochlo v'Shilo v'acharei shato, after she ate
in שילה Shilo and after he drank. שתו ולא
שתתה, shato v'lo shatetah, שתו shato is read like the drinking, but
not her drinking. So therefore you see that she didn't drink. אלא
מעתה, Ela me'atah, says the גמרא, Gemara, אכלו ולא אכלה? ochlo v'lo
achlah? Should we read the first word about אכלו ochlo with a
ה hey to mean she ate but he didn't eat? Which I'm
not going to try to unpack all this. It's very confusing what
the גמרא Gemara is getting at here. הכי נמי? Hachi nami? No.
אנן בשינוי קרא בדיבורא
קאמרינן. Anan b'shinui k'ra b'dibura ka'amrinan. We're saying because the פסוק pasuk
changed what it should have said. מכדי דגברא קאמר. michdi d'gavra ka'amar.
He was talking about חנה Chana ואתי. ve-ati. מאי טעמא שני? mai
ta'ama shani? Why did it say, why did it say? תוספות Tosafot
basically said it should have said אכלה ושתתה akhla veshatata and her
drinking. Why did it say ושתה? veshato? So מאי טעמא שני, mai
ta'ama shani, שמע מינה shema mina ושתה, shato, the drinking, ולא שתתה,
velo shatet, not her drinking. All right, so whatever that דרשה drasha
is. מיתיבי: Meitivei: רגילה נותנין לה. regila nosnin lah.
We have a ברייתא braita that says if a woman is accustomed
to drinking wine, we do allocate wine for her. Okay, רגילה שאני,
regila shani, if she's accustomed, it's different. Then she can handle it,
she's developed the tolerance. דאמר רבי חנינא בר כהנא אמר שמואל: de-amar
Rabbi Chanina bar Kahana amar Shmuel: רגילה נותנין לה כוס אחד. regila
nosnin lah kos echad. If a woman is accustomed, we do give
her one glass, I don't know what that means per day, per
week, probably per day, because they would say if you were accustomed
to it, you would drink wine at every meal. Okay, שאינה רגילה,
she-eina regila, if she's not accustomed, נותנין לה שני כוסות. nosnin lah
shenei kosos. Then you give her two glasses. אביי Abaye says: מאי
קאמרת? mai ka-amart? What are you saying? So אמר אביי הכי קאמר.
amar Abaye hakhi ka-amar. Here's what you're saying: רגילה בפני בעלה שני
כוסות. regila bifnei ba'alah shenei kosos. If normally when she's with her
husband she drinks two cups of wine at each meal, then שלא
בפני בעלה, she-lo bifnei ba'alah, when she's apart from her husband, he's
away on a business trip or whatever the case might be and
בית דין beis din is allocating, then נותנין לה כוס אחד. nosnin
lah kos echad. Then you give her one cup. אינה רגילה בפני
בעלה אלא כוס אחד, eina regila bifnei ba'alah ela kos echad, if
she only has one cup when her husband's around, שלא בפני בעלה
אין נותנין לה כל עיקר. she-lo bifnei ba'alah ein nosnin lah kol
ikar. You don't give her anything. Now how to read that into
the line of שמואל Shmuel I don't understand, תוספות Tosafot tries to
read it in, but anyway the point is even if she is
accustomed, you give her less than when her husband is around because
again we're afraid that without
her husband maybe she's not having her sexual desires met and her
husband isn't there to sort of rein her in and all these
other assumptions that the גמרא Gemara is making, and therefore we have
to be more careful. So even if she's accustomed, you give her
less, and if she's accustomed to only one, you give her nothing.
They need to go to Al-Anon.
ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'it eima, okay, and if you want I can say
רגילה, regila, even if she's accustomed, you don't give her wine for
her to drink without her husband, but נותנין לה לציקי קדרה. nosnin
lah le-tsikei kdera. You give her for to add to the stew,
right, because sometimes you use wine as a cooking ingredient, so but
you wouldn't give her any wine to drink without her husband being
around. אמר רב אבא אמר רבי יוחנן מעשה בכלתו של נקדימון בן
גוריון. amar Rav Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan ma'aseh bi-khalato shel Nakdimon ben
Guryon. The story with the daughter-in-law of נקדימון בן גוריון Nakdimon ben
Guryon שפסקו לה חכמים סאתיים יין לציקי
קדרה. she-pasku lah chakhamim sata'im yayin le-tsikei kdera. The rabbis allocated for
her two סאה se'ah of wine for the for her for cooking,
מערב שבת לערב שבת, me-erev Shabbos le-erev Shabbos, from
on a weekly basis. אמרה להם, amra lahem, she said to them:
כך תפסקו לבנותיכם. kakh tifsaku li-venoseikhem. So, you know, she was at,
it sounds like, you know, you never know if this is ironic
or not, but it sounds like she was happy and she said,
"Oh, thank you so much, that was so generous, you should also
merit that your daughters also should be in similar situations, I guess,"
assuming it was serious and not ironic. Okay, and she'd get that
amount of wine. תנא: tanna: שומרת יבם
היתה, shomeres yavam hayesa, she actually was a waiting יבום, yibbum, ולא
ענו אחריה
אמן. velo anu achareiha amen. And they didn't say אמן amen because
then it would have been like a bad סימן, siman, it would
have meant that their daughters-in-law would have, you know, or their daughters
would be, their husbands would die on them. But now by the
way we're also implicitly seeing why the rabbis are allocating. As opposed
to the husband being alive but being away on a trip or
just them living apart for whatever reason, he could also be dead.
And remember, one of the תנאי כתובה tenai kesuvah that the woman
is provided for from the dead husband's estate. So how do you
determine how much food she gets from the dead husband's estate? You
would presumably use a similar type of guidelines as our משנה. mishna.
So this משנה mishna could be very important for the ongoing support
of the אלמנה. almanah. So a woman awaiting יבום yibbum is also
the אלמנה almanah of the dead husband, so they are determining what
is her ongoing support from the estate.
Wait, when the גמרא Gemara says like נותנין לה, nosnin lah, like
two cups, like in other words, what does that look like? The
servant who's in charge of the estate?
No, she comes to בית דין beis din and she and the
heirs come to בית דין beis din and she basically says, "I
need my food provided for me." So the בית דין beis din
figures out what food she's entitled to and determines how much they
have to provide for on a weekly basis. Whether they write out
a check or whether they actually provide her with the food itself.
But in other words, what it means is they give her the
amount of money that would enable her to have that much food.
Well, the משנה mishna makes it sound like they actually give it,
because the משנה mishna says if he doesn't have this fruit, he
gives her fruit from another, he gives her other fruit. So it
sounds like he literally is giving her this actual... look, it would
be much more convenient for me if somebody wants to make a
delivery of groceries to my door than just gives me a check
and I have to go out and shop. So if this is
really the amount that she would use, it'd be much better for
her to actually get the food itself directly delivered, right? But if
we basically wind up that he gives her a check and then
she decides, "I'm not going to have my pressed dates today, I'm
gonna use some of that money to buy wine," nobody's going to
stop her. But if we're actually providing, if we're figuring out how
big that check should be or actually providing her the food itself.
You're delivering a certain amount of wine.
Exactly. So we're not delivering, well, the point is we're not delivering
the wine unless it's for cooking purposes. Okay. So now we get
to what's underlying all this hesitancy. תנא: tanna: כוס אחד יפה לאשה.
kos echad yafeh le-isha. One glass of wine, that's good for a
woman. שנים, shnayim, and as we've seen before maybe even that only
if her husband's around, שנים ניוול הוא. shnayim nival hu. Two, it's
like it's unseemly, I think that's a good translation. שלושה תובעת בפה,
shlosha tova'at b'peh, once she has three glasses of wine she'll basically
verbally demand sex from some whoever whatever whatever not just vulgar, she'll
actually proposition men for sex.
ארבעה, arba'ah, four, אפילו חמור תובעת בשוק, afilu chamor tova'at bashuk, even
if she sees a donkey in the marketplace she'll try to have
sex with it, ואינה אכפת לה v'aina ikpat lah and she doesn't
care. So anyway, this is obviously another גמרא Gemara being written by
men. Also in the society where women had less wine, so actually
probably they probably did have less of a tolerance for it, but
still it's pretty extreme what it sort of assumes. אמר רבא: amar
Rava: לא שנו אלא שאין בעלה עמה, lo shanu ela she'ein ba'alah
imah, all of this as we've sort of been implying before is
if the husband isn't around. אבל בעלה עמה לית לן בה, aval
ba'alah imah leit lan bah, nobody is going to tell her if
she's with her husband, this is the husband isn't there and it's
בית דין's beit din responsibility to determine whether to give her wine
or not, how much for her, how much you know food to
provide for her. If she's with her husband, nobody is going to
tell her, you know her or her husband that they can't decide
to have wine together. Okay. A, we assume that the husband will
more protect her, you know will more stop you know protect against
certain behavior, but also I would say more significantly, it's none of
our business, right? Are you so so therefore you know it's only
our business if her husband isn't around and we're the ones providing
the food. והא, v'ha, the גמרא Gemara says והא חנה דבעלה עמה
הוי, v'ha Chana d'ba'alah imah havai, one minute, Hannah was there with
her husband when they were you know in שילה, Shilo, and it
says and we made the whole דרשה drasha that she didn't drink
wine. So you said it's okay to drink wine if a woman's
with her husband? So the גמרא Gemara says no, אכסנאי שאני, achsanai
shani, there they were guests, they weren't at home. דאמר רב הונא:
d'amar Rav Huna: מנין לאכסנאי שאסור בתשמיש המטה? minayin l'achsanai she'asur b'tashmish
hamitah? How do you know if you're a guest at somebody's house
and they give you a bedroom that you know husband and wife
shouldn't be having
sex? שנאמר: shene'emar: וישכימו בבקר וישתחוו לפני ה', vayashkimu baboker vayishtachavu lifnei
Hashem, they rose up in the morning and they bowed down to
God, וישבו ויבאו אל ביתם הרמתה, vayashuvu vayavo'u el beitam haramatah, they
came back to their home in רמה, Ramah, וידע אלקנה את חנה
אשתו, vayeida Elkanah et Chana ishto, and only then they had sex.
ויזכרה ה'. vayizkereha Hashem. השתא אין מעיקרא לא, hashta in mei'ikara lo,
only now, not before. So you have to be much more careful
about your behavior even if it's okay in the privacy of your
own home, but when you're a guest in somebody else's home, you
have to be more careful, whether it's about having sex and whether
it's about drinking wine and so on, getting carried away, etc. Okay.
Now we're going to have some stories. חומא דביתהו דאביי, Choma d'veiteihu
d'Abaye, Homa who was Abaye's wife, who apparently was very beautiful,
אתאי לקמיה דרבא, ata'i l'kamei d'Rava, she came to Rava, and apparently
Abaye was away on some teaching trip. אמרה ליה: amrah leh: פסוק
לי מזוני, psok li mezoni, do you know determine for me allocate
for me the food that I can be provided for.
פסקה, paskah, so he figured it out, he wrote out the amount
in you know he gave her whatever from בית דין beit din
that would entitle her to collect that amount of food from the
estate. Okay.
פסקה. paskah. פסוק לי חמרא, psok li chamra, so now wait, there's
no wine on this list, allocate for me wine.
אמר לה: amar lah: ידענא ביה בנחמני, yadana bih b'Nachmani, I know
Nachmani, which is Abaye's name,
דלא הוה שתי חמרא, d'lo havah shati chamra, he wouldn't drink wine.
אמרה ליה, amrah leh, so she said back to him: חיי דמר,
chayei d'mar, by the life of the master, by your life, דהוה
משקי לי בשופריזי, d'havah mashki li b'shufrizi, he would actually
drink for drink wine in שופריזי shufrizi in like a horn or
like an elongated cup, כי האי, ki hai, this big, this big
of a cup, she like held out her hand, he would drink
wine, which by the way echoes the previous point of the גמרא
Gemara that people do things in private that they don't do in
public. Because Rava says, I know he never drank wine! She says,
a lot you know, I'll tell you he drank wine, okay. בהדי
דקא מחויא ליה, bahadei d'ka machvaya leh,
as she was demonstrating to him like this big of a cup
and holding out her arms, איגלי דרעא, iglei d'ra'ah, her arm became
exposed, like the sleeve fell down her arm. נפל נהורא בבי דינא,
nafal nehora b'vei dina, and light shone in the בי דינא bei
dina or her arm was her skin was so beautiful, it was
like a glowing according to the בית המדרש. beit hamidrash. קם רבא,
kam Rava, so Rava got up, he was very disturbed, as we'll
see he was very sexually excited. על לביתיה, al l'veiteih, he went
home, תבעה לבת רב חסדא, tav'ah l'bat Rav Chisda, and he propositioned
his wife who was the daughter of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, and
basically had sex with her in the middle of the day. אמרה
ליה, amrah leh, so בת רב חסדא, bat Rav Chisda, so his
wife said to him: מאן הוה האידנא בבי דינא, man havah idna
b'vei dina, what happened today in court, honey?
אמר לה: amar lah: חומא דביתהו
דאביי, Choma d'veiteihu d'Abaye, well, Homa, Abaye's wife came to court. נפקה
בתרה, nafkah batrah, so Rava's wife ran after her, מחייתא בקופי דשידא,
machyata b'kofei d'shida, and hit her with the strap from the from
a chest, עד דאפקתה מכולה מחוזא, ad d'afaktah mikulah Mechuza, until she
chased her from the whole city of מחוזא, Mechuza, because she said
this woman was just going to lead men or her husband astray.
אמרה לה: amrah lah: קטלת ליה. katlat leh. You've already killed three
men. She apparently had been married three times and every single time
her husband had died. Okay, not exactly clear to me, maybe this
third time was אביי Abaye who had died and that's why she
was coming to the court to get the food, because maybe אביי
Abaye had died, although it doesn't, it's not clear, doesn't say that.
I'm trying to figure out why she's in the court to get
the food and now we're finding out that her husband had died
three times. Okay, and now that she had three husbands, not her
husband died three times.
She had three husbands, each of whom had died. Okay, so you've
already killed three, ואתא למיקטל אחרינא ve-assa le-miketal achrina and now you
want to kill a fourth? Like, you know, your beauty is going
to lead yet another man astray, and now he's going to die,
my husband probably, and he's going to die, which makes sense therefore
given that that it could be that אביי Abaye was dead, which
is why they were coming to the court to get the מזונות,
Mezonot, but maybe not. Okay, moving on.
What does her name mean?
I don't know. Moving on. Okay. דביתהו דרב יוסף בריה דרבא, De-viseihu
de-Rav Yosef berei de-Rava, the wife of רב יוסף Rav Yosef the
son of רבא, Rava, אתאי לקמיה דרב נחמיה בריה דרב יוסף, asei
le-kamei de-Rav Nechemia berei de-Rav Yosef, came by רב נחמיה Rav Nechemia
the son of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, not clear if it's the
same or a different רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמרה ליה, amrah lei,
she said to him, פסוק לי מזוני, psok li mezoni, allocate for
me מזונות, Mezonot, again my husband is either dead or away, whatever
it is. פסק לה, pasak lah, he wrote, you know, he allocated.
פסוק לי חמרא, psok li chamra, how about wine? פסק לה, pasak
lah, he wrote it out for her. אמר לה, amar lah, so
he said to her, ידנא בהו בבני מחוזא, yadana behu bi-venei Mechuza,
I know the people of מחוזא, Mechuza, which is again, which said
דשתו חמרא, de-shasu chamra, that they drink wine, so for you coming
from that town, drinking wine is like a regular, like if you
go to France, right? You know, I don't know, I never grew
up as a, you know, for me what
we had at dinner was either water or if you were an
adult you got to drink soda. You know, you go to other
places, it's like they drink wine at every single meal. You know,
you go to France, they drink wine at every single meal. So
anyway, so where you are determines on whether this is considered something
dangerous or something normal to be allocating the wine. Okay.
דביתהו דרב יוסף בריה דרב מנשיא מדויאל, De-viseihu de-Rav Yosef berei de-Rav
Menashya mi-Deviel, so the wife of רב יוסף Rav Yosef the son
of
רב מנשיא Rav Menashya of דויאל... Deviel...